<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Strang Splitting | Valentina Schüller</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/strang-splitting/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/strang-splitting/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Strang Splitting</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2024 11:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Strang Splitting</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/strang-splitting/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waveform Relaxation for Coupled Groundwater and Surface Flows</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/event/pint_2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/event/pint_2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Water management projects such as stream bed re-naturalization affect the water table, which is relevant, e.g., for flood prediction. These physical processes can be modeled by coupling the Richards equation for groundwater flow to a shallow water model for rivers or lakes (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi-org.ludwig.lub.lu.se/10.1007/978-3-642-25100-9_65&#34;&gt;Bastian et al., 2012&lt;/a&gt;). We analyzed the fully discrete, linearized formulation of this coupling problem, yielding an optimal choice of the relaxation parameter for sequential Dirichlet-Neumann iterations. Here we followed the techniques previously established in &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi-org.ludwig.lub.lu.se/10.1007/s00466-017-1511-3&#34;&gt;Monge &amp;amp; Birken, 2018&lt;/a&gt;. This analysis is closely linked to parallel Dirichlet-Neumann iterations, which are a special case of parallel-in-time waveform relaxation. Waveform relaxation methods have been extensively studied in continuous or semi-discrete formulations. As we will show in this talk, the fully discrete analysis—corresponding to the actual implementation in a numerical model—can give significantly different results. Our theoretical analysis is supported by numerical results for a fully nonlinear test case using &lt;a href=&#34;https://dune-project.org/&#34;&gt;DUNE&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://precice.org/&#34;&gt;preCICE&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Simple Test Case for Error Reduction of Black-Box Coupling Schemes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/event/gacm_2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 15:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/event/gacm_2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Black-box coupling libraries such as preCICE support sophisticated methods to enable accurate and efficient multiphysics simulations (e.g., regarding data mapping or coupling scheme acceleration).
However, sticking to standard coupling schemes can easily decrease the achievable convergence order of the numerical solution, specifically with respect to time integration; a phenomenon we call order degradation.
To understand these effects (and possible solutions), we want to study specifically the interaction of coupling schemes and time integration methods. &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this talk, we present and analyze a simple test case of two masses connected with springs; we use it to isolate the impact of the coupling scheme on the overall accuracy and energy conservation of a partitioned simulation. We show issues arising for combinations of traditionally used coupling schemes and common time integration methods. We demonstrate that these two components interact with each other, which can lead to surprisingly good and bad results. Continuing the analysis, we confirm how Strang splitting and waveform iterations can reduce or even prevent order degradation. Additionally, we analyze their impact on energy conservation. &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Strang splitting and waveform iterations are discussed with respect to their applicability in full-scale multiphysics applications. We finally give an outlook on an extension of the test case to study the convergence of waveform iterations for subcycling and multirate time stepping. This enables us to also cover applications with a multiscale characteristic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Simple Test Case for Convergence Order in Time and Energy Conservation of Black-Box Coupling Schemes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publication/fsi-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publication/fsi-paper/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The oscillator example for testing black-box coupling schemes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/fsi_coupling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 16:47:47 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/fsi_coupling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I developed this small code base together with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.cit.tum.de/sccs/personen/benjamin-rodenberg/&#34;&gt;Benjamin Rodenberg&lt;/a&gt; following a seminar on multiphysics simulation.
We used it to study both convergence order in time as well as energy conservation for common black-box coupling schemes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/valentinaschueller/oscillator-example&#34;&gt;Code available on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scipedia.com/public/Rodenberg_2022a&#34;&gt;Full paper available on Scipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
